Abi Mikaiil Abdulahad

Raleigh, NC, 27606 M: (919) 759-1884 ustezabdulahad@gmail.com

CAREER SUMMARY

I am a confident career educator, teacher trainer, student advisor, and mentor with several years of culturally responsive language teaching and training experience with a strong track record of improving students' success through reflective and responsive differentiated teaching and guidance. I am interested in contributing to a dynamic educational institution that values ongoing professional development and offers a genuine opportunity for career progression.

EDUCATION

- 2017- M.Ed. International Education, American International College
- 2014- Bachelor of Arts in English Language Learner Studies, Ashford University
- 2011- Associates of Arts in Elementary Education, Axia College of Phoenix University

CERTIFICATIONS

- CELTA, Cambridge/British Council
- 2004- TEFL Certificate/Diploma, I to I Online TEFL (British) Distant Learning Course
- 2004- TESOL/Basic Literacy Certificate Literacy, Volunteers of America
- K-6 Licensure in progress
- Temporary licensure to teach K-6 General Education and ESoL

SKILLS & SPECIALIZED TRAINING

- TSA Workshop CITA Workshop-Teaching Theory Life Skills Coaching
- CPR/First Aid Microsoft Office, Microsoft Teams, Classroom Screen, Zoom

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

5th Grade ELA/Social Sciences Teacher

Triangle Math and Science Academy, Apex, NC

2024 - present

- Develop students' knowledge about global and national social issues, understanding the geographical, historical, cultural and political factors that influence the development of world regions providing students with prompt and meaningful discussions and instructional feedback
- Efficiently and successfully taught American English Language Arts & Literature combined with ELL methods to ensure students could access literary texts appropriately while training students in effective study methods for success on assessments
- Effectively differentiate instruction to meet the varied learning needs of students
- Work individually and collaboratively with other teachers to design instructional plans, design assessments, analyze student achievement data, use technology to support instruction, and adjust plans as necessary to help students master the content
- Utilize core curriculum and other appropriate tools such as Infinite Campus for grading and Clever, NWEA for assessment that informs curriculum and instruction
- Participate in ongoing professional development through professional learning communities

Middle-school Social Sciences Teacher

Cardinal Charter Academy, Cary, NC

2023 - 2024

- Develop students' knowledge about global and national social issues, understanding the geographical, historical, cultural and political factors that influence the development of world regions providing students with prompt and meaningful discussions and instructional feedback
- Work individually and collaboratively with other teachers to design instructional plans, design assessments, analyze student achievement data, use technology to support instruction, and adjust plans as necessary to help students master the content
- Effectively differentiate instruction to meet the varied learning needs of students
- Utilize core curriculum and other appropriate tools such as Powerschool for grading and Schoology for PLCs and virtual learning

Director of Programming and Student Development

AGE- American Goals and Education, Hybrid

2009 - Present

- Create and curate both core curriculum and supplemental resources to strengthen the overall curriculum and evaluate the effectiveness of the curriculum and resources through the analysis of student performance data
- Research, develop, direct, implement, and monitor first-year student success program as
 well as programs designed to support students at various levels with specific
 developmental needs to increase student success

Student Advisor/ESL Teacher

An-Noor Academy; Raleigh, NC

2021-2022

- Passionately provided a student centered, supportive classroom while addressing academic needs; provided significant student mentoring and advising
- Consistently promoted compassion and tolerance, emotional security, resourcefulness, and independent critical thinking while addressing the emotional needs of each student through a differentiated approach
- Developed and maintained genuine, positive, and consistent communication with parents and school community which included active speaking engagements

High/Middle School Student Success Advisor/ English and Writing Teacher GHARS Bilingual Schools; Kuwait

2019-2021

- Focused on student youth interrelated areas of Social Emotional Learning competences in the areas of self-awareness, self-management, social awareness, relationship skills, and responsible decision-making
- Encouraged self-pathways to postsecondary educational and/or vocational attainment.
- Creatively used various tools such as PowerPoint media presentations, videos, and articles to improve students' comprehension of the English language for use in higher education and real-world applications

Academic Advisor/Instructor

Noor Bilingual School; Kuwait

2017-2019

- Routinely and effectively advised students using tailored-made success plans to address specific learning needs and goals
- Led one-on-one and small group sessions with students to help them overcome barriers and access available academic and social emotional resources

- Prepared and implemented lessons that encourage and foster proficient oral and written expression, critical thinking, applications, and ethics
- Openly communicated and collaborated with parents and school administration in a
 professional capacity to discuss education-based cultural challenges impeding success
 and ways to improve student attendance and performance

High School English Teacher

Egyptian American International School; New Cairo

2015-2016

- Developed and implemented individualized action plans for students' educational advancement
- Focused on building rapport with students while creating a safe learning climate
- Efficiently and successfully taught American English literature combined with ELL methods to ensure high school ESL students could access literary context appropriately while training students in effective study methods for success on assessments
- Mentored and advised students preparing for college by providing real world applications and general life expectations

Middle School Humanities Teacher

Al Huda School/Darussalam; College Park, MD

2014-2015

- Taught ELA, Social Studies, and Math to 6-8th graders while maintaining effective classroom behavior management
- Developed simplified lesson plans in line with curriculum objectives and school policies
- Focused greatly on using effective means toward student advising and mentoring